Guide to the Northwest Tribal Oral History interviews 1963-1973
Center for Pacific Northwest Studies
Northwest Tribal Oral History interviews
1963-1973 1973
1973
Center for Pacific Northwest Studies
XOE_CPNWS0067nwtriba
2 linear feet
Includes first-hand accounts of members and elders of Native American tribes in Washington State and Idaho who provide information on long-standing traditions such as language, education, genealogy, politics, religion, as well as hunting and fishing practices.
The Northwest Tribal Oral History Project was initially produced under the direction of Dr. Donald Eklund, Associate Professor of History at Western Washington University and Professor Jeffery Wilner also of Western Washington University. In 1999-2000, the collection was described and duplicated by Stacy Rasmus of the Lummi Language and Cultural Department as part of a joint project between the Lummi Indian Nation and the Center for Pacific Northwest Studies.
The Northwest Tribal Oral History interviews contains information pertaining to a wide variety of Native American tribes and peoples in Washington State and Idaho. The interviews reflect perspectives of tribe members as well as elders. The majority of these interviews are conducted with both members and elders of the Lummi and the Nooksack tribes. Other interviewees include members and elders from the Chinook, Chehalis, Cowlitz, Pachenant, Quinault, Colville, Sinkiuse, and Swinomish tribes. There is also an interview with a member of the Nez Perce Tribe. Some topics discussed in these interviews and recordings include Native American languages and word etymologies, religion, education, genealogy, songs, hunting and fishing as well as politics. Also contained within the collection are recordings of the Northwest Indians Executive Council meetings and conferences held in Spokane, WA in 1973.
Although the material in Northwest Tribal Oral History interviews span from 1963-1973, the majority of it dates from 1973. Eighteen interviews out of the fifty four audio tapes have transcriptions. Due to the age of the audio cassette recordings, some tapes are completely inaudible.
The Northwest Tribal Oral History interviews is organized in accordance with the following series arrangement:
Series I: Audio Recordings, 1963-1973
Series II: Transcripts, 1967-1973
The collection is open to the public.
Eklund, Don.; Wilner, Jeffrey D.
Quinault Indians--Washington (State)--History--Sources.; Lummi Indians--Washington (State)--History--Sources.; Salish Indians--Washington (State)--History--Sources.; Chehalis Indians--Washington (State)--History--Sources.; Chinook Indians--Washington (State)--History--Sources.; Nooksack Indians--Washington (State)--History--Sources.; Nez Percé Indians--Idaho--History--Sources.; Colville Indians--Washington (State)--History--Sources.; Yakama Indians--Washington (State)--History--Sources.; Cowlitz Indians--Washington (State)--History--Sources.; Coast Salish Indians--Washington (State)--History -- Sources.; Swinomish Indians--Washington (State)--History -- Sources.; Indians of North America--Washington (State)--Social life and customs--History--Sources.; Indians of North America--Washington (State)--Agriculture -- History--Sources.; Indians of North America--Washington (State)--Fishing--Law and legislation--History--Sources.; Indians of North America--Washington (State)--History -- Sources.; Indians of North America--Education--Washington (State)--History --Sources.; Indians of North America--Washington (State)--Folklore--History --Sources.; Indians of North America--Washington (State)--Languages--History --Sources.; Indians of North America--Fishing--Washington (State)--History -- Sources.; Indians of North America--Hunting--Washington (State)--History -- Sources.; Indians of North America--Washington (State)--Government relations --History--Sources.; Indians of North America--Washington (State)--Religion--History --Sources.; Indians of North America--Washington (State)--Social Conditions -- History--Sources.; Indians of North America--Washington (State)--Treaties--History --Sources.; Indians of North America--Washington (State)--Art--History -- Sources.; Indians of North America--Washington (State)--Music--History -- Sources.
Oral histories.; Interviews (Sound recordings)
Native Americans; Washington (State); Missionaries; Oral Histories
- Audio Recordings, 1963-1973; Series I; 33999
  - Vern Dunning, Chehalis Pioneer, on the Chinook Language, 1965 September 23 (Box 1, Tape 1)
    Tape, 1, Side One: Vern Dunning speaks about origin and composition of Chinook jargon and counts in Chinook Jargon. Dunning speaks about varieties of language among the tribes along the Columbia and North Pacific Coast that made a trade or universally understood language (pidgin) necessary. Dunning goes over vocabulary in Chinook jargon. "King George Man" is an Englishman. Gives names for coat and canoe. [The quality of the tape is not so good as to be able to discern the pronunciation of the Chinook Jargon words absolutely.] Tum-tum meaning the beat of the heart - Tum River. Memaloose - to die, Memaloose Island. Hýoo - big, huge, a lot. Skookum, strong. Chickema, money. Dunning constructs sentences in Chinook Jargon. Chook, grandma, grandpa. Chuck, water. Dunning gives explanation of some of the words, how they degraded from their original English, French or Indian pronunciation. Ickta, what. Iskum, to get. Dunning notes the difference between the English pronunciation of Chinook Jargon and the Indian pronunciation where the "k" sound is replaced by the "g" sound by the Indians that Dunning has spoken with. Klootchman, wife, woman. Kootman, mare. Kuntucks, to understand, knowledge, recognize or believe. Piljob, the devil. Mosh, to leave, turn out, sail, throw away, quit, vanish, cast, dash, desert, dispatch, dismiss, detach, drop, apply, expel, exterminate, forsake, heave, insert, relinquish, remit, sling, toss, transmit etc. Speaks the contextual nature of Chinook Jargon. Mumook, to work. Nesatchi, bad, evil. Moose-moose, horned cattle. Mowwich, deer. Moosum, to sleep. Muck-a-muck, food. Mika, second person, you. Dunning speaks about learning Chinook Jargon from the Indian children around his home as a child fishing in the Chehalis River.
    Tape 1, Side Two:Tillicum, friend. Ticook, white. Tum-water, waterfall. Tyee, chief. Tenas, small. Wa-wa, speak or talk. Dunning speaks about the guttural nature of Chinook Jargon. Dunning speaks about being born in Quincy, Michigan. Dunning speaks about the railway system and traveling from Michigan by train to the Northwest. Interview concludes noting that Vern Dunning was reading through the book Chinook: A History and Dictionary, by Edward Harper Thomas, and examining a "birds-eye" picture of Centralia in 1884.
  - Silas Heck, Chehalis Shaker, 1963 (Box 1, Tape 2)
    Tape 2, Side One [Tape speed varies]: Silas Heck & Vern Dunning speak about the use of Chinook Jargon. Heck speaks about fur trading. Silas Heck speaks of the origination of the Chinook Jargon with the Hudson's Bay company. [Chinook Jargon was not a product of the contact brought about through the fur trade, it existed among the tribes along the Columbia and Coast who did not share a common dialect. The fur trade exacerbated its use.] Silas Heck speaks about his father trapping for beaver. Heck recalls his father living with the Ford family. Heck speaks about how Lizzie Ford and his father produced a child, with the last name Pickner, Reilly Pickner. Heck speaks about how Reilly Pickner and Pickner's family were not recognized by anyone as part Indian. Heck speaks about gathering camas and cedar. Dunning and Heck recall Ford's log house. Heck recalls Governor Stevens holding council at Ford's house to have the treaty read and interpreted. Dunning and Heck speak about Ford's cemetery. Heck speaks about being a Shaker, of the John Slocum denomination. Heck tells the story of John Slocum's death and resurrection, which marked the foundation of the Shaker religion. Heck speaks about what happens after death. Heck speaks about Wickasham's recollection of life after death. Heck speaks about being chief of police on the reservation. Heck continues to recount John Slocum's travels after death. Heck speaks about Slocum's promise of a new medicine for the people. Heck recounts how the coming of the medicine that makes up the "shaking" part of the church. Heck speaks about his living relations. Dunning speaks about living in Centralia. Heck speaks about Billy Mills and the Mills family who could speak the Chehalis language. Heck speaks about the importance of camas for his people, and who camas was utilized by the white people also. [Tape goes out, portion of interview lost]. Heck speaks about the preparation of camas. Heck speaks about hunting elk, most opportune times etc. Heck speaks about the medicine man of the early times, which worked as healers as well as seers.
    Tape 2, Side Two: Blank for about two minutes. Heck speaks about the coming of the white people as foreseen by the medicine men of the early days, who brought domestication. [Tape goes out] Heck continues speaking about animal domestication. Heck speaks about his religious beliefs. Integration of the teachings of Jesus Christ into Native American spiritual life. Heck gives his Indian name in the Chehalis language, Ts'e may'uks. Heck gives his age as 91. Heck discusses his views of Native American origin in North America; he speaks of his people being the people of the lost tribe of Israel. Heck speaks about playing the bone game. [Tape cuts out]
  - Pachenant Indian Reserve, 1973 (Box 1, Tape 3)
    Tape 3, Side One: Tape begins with introduction, by Randy Lewis of Western Washington University. He is taping his travels to the Pachenant Indian Reserve, which is a fishing village town of Port Rentview, on the West Coast side of Vancouver Island. The entire tape is a narrative by Randy Lewis, as he acknowledges that the Pachenant are hostile to outsiders. He notes that to interview a tribal member requires a permission process approved only through the Tribal Council. Lewis speaks about the betrayal of the early anthropologists and sociologists that have made the Pechenant cautious about trusting outside researchers. Lewis will discuss the conversation he had with Chief Art Jones of the Pachenant people. Lewis speaks about visiting the past acting Chief, Charlie Jones. Lewis attests to his Indian heritage. Lewis describes Chief Art Jones, his character and appearance, and role as a traditional chief. Lewis discusses the history of the Pachenant people, their migrations in the early days and their relations among the other Native groups. Lewis recounts Chief Art Jones talking about the education of his people (which he refers to as his children). Lewis recounts Chief Art Jones speaking about the building reforms on the reserve. Lewis describes Chief Art Jones' concern for identify loss among his people due to Western education and influences. Lewis describes revitalization projects underway on the reserve. Lewis discusses the housing project on the Pachenant reserve. Lewis speaks about the income of the Pachenant people, which is almost entirely dependent on the lumber industry. Lewis relates Chief Art Jones' reasons why the Pachenant do not salmon fish. The main reasons are the expense of the equipment needed to be competitive in the commercial fish market and the governmental restrictions by the Canadian government on salmon retailing and harvesting by the Indians.
    Tape 3, Side Two: Lewis continues to speak about the income of the Pachenant. Lewis discusses the relations between the Pachenant and the white community at Port Rentview. Lewis relates the story of a murder of a young Pachenant Indian man by a white man of Port Rentview. This murder and the overall prejudice of the white community has made relations hostile. Lewis attests to the mending of relations between the Pachenant and the white community by Chief Art Jones. Lewis speaks about the problems that Chief Art Jones faces trying to lead his people. Lewis speaks about the problems of higher education for the young Indian people. Lewis speaks about the fishing rights of the Pachenant people, which is heavily restricted by the treaty made with the British. Lewis relates the fishing provisions of the Pachenant people by telling a story Chief Art Jones told him in their interview about the prosecution of the previous Chief Charlie Jones for fishing violations. Lewis speaks about Chief Art Jones' wish and plan to bring his people back to the reserve, i.e. annuities for returning members. Lewis speaks about social problems among the Pachenant community. Lewis speaks about the importance of the children for Pachenant people.
  - George O. Pablo, Flathead counselor at Yakima, and Beatrice Black, Quinault interviewed by David Tuck, undated (Box 1, Tape 4)
    Tape 4, Side One: George Pablo begins by introducing himself as a counselor for Native Americans in Yakima and along the coast to Canada. [Tape is of poor quality and cannot be understood. It gets a bit better after about five minutes.] Pablo speaks about the alcohol treatment programs on the reservation. Pablo speaks about the effects of alcohol on the young Indian people. Pablo speaks about the programs in place to help Indian people combat alcoholism. Pablo speaks about the nature of Indian people that keeps them from speaking out publicly. David Tuck asks about the acceptance level for the Indian Reorganization Act. Pablo speaks about the self-sufficiency of his people. Pablo speaks about the white-Indian relations in his area. Pablo attests to the movement of Indian people to the Urban areas, off the reservation. David Tuck asks about Pablo's knowledge of traditional Flathead ways. Pablo speaks about the retention of traditional hunting and fishing ways. Pablo speaks about the Shakers and about traditional religion, the "Feather religion" or "Bluejay religion." Pablo speaks about the Flathead language. David Tuck asks about myths or legends. Pablo dodges the question. Tuck tries to bait him into telling a legend. Pablo speaks briefly about the coyote. Tuck asks about the function of oral tradition in modern Native American life. Pablo speaks briefly about the retention of traditional ways. Pablo speaks about the Flathead reservation. Pablo speaks about the retention of smoke shacks on the Flathead reservation. Pablo speaks about the dams and the timber as the major sources of income on the Flathead reservation.
    Tape 4, Side Two: [Very poor recording.] Beatrice Black speaks about the traditional ways of travel by canoe on the river systems. Black speaks about walking the beach to get to a place. Black speaks about her brother, who hunted whale and seal. Black speaks about her father's homestead outside of Flatbush. Black speaks about obtaining and selling fish in her day. Black speaks about her father picking hops yearly. Black speaks about using cattails for mats, and where to find cattails. Beatrice Black speaks about gathering grasses. Black speaks about taking a canoe from Neah Bay to Seattle and then sleeping on the dock. Black speaks about traveling to Canada to fish the Fraser River. Black speaks about hunting sea lion. Black speaks about whale watching teams and whale hunting. Beatrice Black speaks about whale hunting. Black speaks about the cataloging of the whale meat. Black speaks about her husband fishing.
  - Ben Charles and Joe De La Cruz, Quinault, interviewed by Clifford Mowitch and Deanna Trotchie, 1973 (Box 1, Tape 5)
    Tape 5, Side One: Clifford Mowitch introduces Ben Charles who is a master carver on the Quinault reservation, who teaches the children. Ben Charles speaks about his beginnings as a wood carver. Ben Charles speaks about teaching carving at Gray's Harbor Community College. Ben Charles specializes in carving canoes and paddles. Ben Charles speaks about carving a 27-foot canoe for the World's Fair in Spokane for the Smithsonian. Ben Charles speaks about his father who was a canoe bearer. Ben Charles speaks about the different kinds of canoes and their functions. All kinds of canoes were made out of red cedar. Shovel-nose canoes. "Half-breed" canoes that were built by the white people were shoveled in the front but built with a place for a motor in the back. Ben Charles speaks about the profits made by the tribe from the carving industry. Deanna Trotchie tries to draw the "meaning" of totem poles out of Ben Charles, but Mr. Charles is not very responsive to her questions. Mr. Charles concedes that the paddles and the totem poles are related to different family lines. A second interview with Tribal Chairman of the Quinault Reservation, Joe De La Cruz begins. Joe De La Cruz begins with a brief history of the tribal council. 1922 as the year of the first set of bylaws adopted by the Quinault. Gives names of previous Chairmen and their relations to the original treaty signers. Explains the Tribal Constitution. Joe De La Cruz speaks about the Allotment Act of 1887, and the effects it had on his people and Quinault land. After the allotment of the reservation the timber companies zoned the timber, and eventually most of it was logged off by long-term contract. Joe De La Cruz speaks of closing off the Reservation, the beach, lake, highway and woods. The logging companies obtained restraining orders from the Federal government, but De La Cruz enforced the closure of the woods on the reservation.
    Tape 5, Side Two: Joe De La Cruz speaks about the monetary loss incurred by the tribe because of their battle to gain autonomy over their timber. De La Cruz speaks on the community outreach programs. Resource development. Resource rehabilitation. Improvement planning. Joe De La Cruz speaks about the beach restrictions, the penalties for trespass by non-Indian etc, and the hunting and clam digging regulations that were redefined by De La Cruz in the Tribal Constitution. De La Cruz speaks about the hatchery on Lake Quinault. Cruz speaks about the houses on the reservation, from the government shacks built in the 1930s to the more modern homes today, that were commissioned in the 1960s. "Self-help" houses.
  - Joe De La Cruz and Nina Baumgardner, interviewed by Clifford Mowitch and Deanna Trotchie, 1973 (Box 1, Tape 6)
    Tape 6, Side One: Joe De La Cruz speaks about the education system for the Quinault people. The addition of Native values and traditions to the standard curriculum to make education more meaningful to the children. Growing rate of Quinault people who attend college. De La Cruz speaks about when his people attended boarding school, mostly at Chemawa. Deanna asks about De La Cruz's feelings towards Wounded Knee. De La Cruz answers. De La Cruz speaks about the steelhead controversy. Washington State banned the sale of game fish, steelhead being a game fish, so tribes sold their steelhead harvest in Oregon while the battle was being fought in court. De La Cruz gives a bit of Quinault history. Primary subsistence during the pre-European contact period. Longhouse locations. Interview ends abruptly. Interview with Nina Baumgardner begins. Nina Baumgardner speaks about shearing sheep in Montana. This discussion leads into a recitation of the twenty-third psalm and her belief in Jesus Christ. Baumgardner speaks about fishing as the primary livelihood of the Quinaults. Nina speaks about attending boarding school at the Puyallup Indian School, which later became known as Cushman Hospital. Motus [Mawtoos] big goings-on, pow-wow, potlatch that she attended with her father put on by Anna Cotes. Nina recalls Puyallup children dipping for salmon on the river. Nina lists some of the prominent family lines of the Puyallup tribe. Nina recalls being brought back to the boarding school from the gathering. Nina speaks about witnessing children fish with a spear in the river. Nina speaks about picking berries. Nina describes a berry scoop that was used to gather loot (root)-berries.
    Tape 6, Side Two: Nina speaks about the lodges, made of split timber and open at the top, that her people use to inhabit. Interview cuts out.
  - Nina Baumgardner, Quinault (Part I), interviewed by Clifford Mowitch and Deanna Trotchie, 1973 May 4 (Box 1, Tape 7)
    Tape 7, Side One: Interview begins in progress with Nina Baumgardner telling of her experience in the Shaker Church. She speaks of the opening and the finishing of the table with a song and a prayer by a sister of the Church. Nina speaks about the apple orchard on North River. Nina describes the processing of the apples. Nina speaks about her family picking apples at the orchard, and her encounter with Sasquatch, Tsi'at'qwes (Ts'emekwes in Lummi). Nina speaks of an encounter with Tsi'at'qwes that her father had on the Nash River. A pear was thrown at her uncle, while there were no pear trees in the area, this is from Ske'kum, something unnatural. Squaxen Island as the headquarters for Tsi'at'qwes. Nina speaks about her holdings on Squaxen Island. Nina speaks about Sasquatch sightings at Gray's Harbor. Nina describes Tsi'at'qwes to her knowledge. Nina speaks about Indian and white relations. Deanna asks about the origin of the Quinault and Nina answers that the Quinault have always been there. Nina addresses the Bering Strait land bridge theory that was described to her as the true origin of her people. Another story claims that the Indian people never did cross the land bridge. Nina recalls speaking to a Mormon missionary, who claimed that Indians were the chosen people. Nina speaks of the "I" that watches you. Nina speaks about her knowledge of the Old and New Testament and upbringing. Nina addresses the belief that Indians are "superstitious." Nina speaks about the sacred nature of water. She tells a fable about water.
    Tape 7, Side Two: Blank
  - Nina Baumgardner, Quinault (Part II), 1973 May 4 (Box 1, Tape 8)
    Tape 8, Side One: Nina Baumgardner speaks about the retaliation to Little Big Horn by the white soldiers on the Sioux. Nina speaks about the unjust nature of the military action against the Indians. Nina speaks about the singing among the Montana Indians. She recalls traveling to many reservations, the Blackfeet, Flathead, Coeur de Lane, Chehalis etc. Nina shows Deanna and others her stash of trade beads (wampum), abalone shells and other objects. Nina speaks about Cushman Indian Boarding School. She recalls beginning school at age six, her homesickness. Nina speaks about her treatment at boarding school. She recalls her sister's experience at St. John's Catholic Boarding School between Seattle and Tacoma, where Native language use was discouraged with physical abuses like lye soap mouthwashes. Nina speaks about working in Seattle during WWII. Nina speaks about Indian hospitality. Nina speaks about attending the Shaker Church. She recalls the singing and dancing. Nina tells the story of the foundation of the Shaker Church with the resurrection of John Slocum. Nina attests to John Slocum belonging to the Squaxen Island people. Nina repeats John Slocum's mission statement that he received from God.
    Tape 8, Side Two: Blank
  - Louie Wapato, Colville (Part I), interviewed by Jeff Wilner, 1973 May 15 (Box 1, Tape 9)